A Guide to the Papers of the National Jazz Hall of Fame, 1974-1988
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the National Jazz Hall of Fame 1974-1988
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10778,-a
This collection consists of ca. 450 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers of the National Jazz Hall of Fame were given to the Library by the Treasurer Henry Thielbar of Charlottesville, Virginia, through Robert Rutland of Charlottesville, Virginia, on August 11, 1988, and October 17, 1988.
Biographical/Historical Information
Robert Rutland, President of the Board of Directors, was a prime mover in the Charlottesville group which met as an ad hoc committee on October 12, 1982 to discuss the feasibility of saving Paramount Theatre and creating the National Jazz Hall of Fame as a vehicle to preserve the movie house and honor the great jazz musicians of America.
The officers of the organization, consisting of a thirteen member board of directors, including a president, vice president, secretary, and treasurer, were responsible for conducting the business of the National Jazz Hall of Fame and to provide a public accounting of the income and expenses during the preceding year. A National Advisory Board was established to act as a liason between the performing artists, critics, and composers and the National Jazz Hall of Fame.
The Board of Directors envisioned a museum with separate rooms devoted to each of the great eras of jazz, New Orleans, Chicago, Ragtime, Big Band, New York and the Village, Kansas City, and the Sound of Our Times, including The Hall of Fame of Jazz honoring the most outstanding musicians and composers, a Center for the Performing Arts, and educational programs and seminars. The organization established to promote the Hall of Fame was incorporated in February 1983 and disbanded in 1988.
Scope and Content Information
These papers consisting of ca. 450 items (3 Hollinger boxes, 1 linear foot), 1974-1988, and undated, contain correspondence, newsclippings, photographs, publicity material, legal papers, and printed material all pertaining to the establishment of a National Jazz Hall of Fame in Charlottesville, Virginia, as a national archive, repository, resource center and promoter of jazz.
Notable correspondents include Whitney Balliett, Leonard Feather, Benny Goodman, Johnson McRee, Jr., Maxine Sullivan, H.J. Swinney, and Paul Tanner. The photographs file contains photographs of the Cotton Club movie set, including Ray Rivera, Duke Ellington, Buddy Rich, and Charlie Bird Parker. Photographs present in the file of their subjects include Louis Armstrong, Leonard Feather, and Maxine Sullivan.
Contents List
- Armstrong, Louis 1983 (Box 1)
- Articles of Incorporation 1985 (Box 1)
- Artists' Biographies 1982-1985, n.d. (Box 1)
- Balliett, Whitney 1983 & 1985 (Box 1)
- Band Directors - Central Virginia n.d. (Box 1)
- Benefit Concert for National Jazz Hall of Fame 1983 Feb 26 (Box 1)
- Bibliography - Jazz Articles n.d. (Box 1)
- Breeden Family Trust 1984-1985 (Box 1)
- British/European Jazz Groups - Publications 1983-1984 (Box 1)
- Brochure for the National Jazz Hall of Fame 1983 (Box 1)
- Charter/Minutes/By-Laws/IRS 1983-1985 (Box 1)
- College Jazz Festival, Charlottesville 1985 Apr 12-14 (Box 1)
- Concerts - Past 1982-1984 (Box 1)
- Concerts - Upcoming 1983-1985 (Box 1)
- Cooper, Martin 1983-1985 (Box 1)
- Correspondence A-N 1982-1985 (Box 1)
- Correspondence O-Z 1982-1988 (Box 1)
- Delaware University 1983 (Box 1)
- Development Campaign & Donations 1983-1985 (Box 1)
- Difficulties of the National Jazz Hall of Fame [1986] (Box 1)
- Downbeat Magazine 1984 Sep (Box 1)
- Educators - National Association of Jazz Educators 1978 (Box 1)
- Educators - Virginia 1983-1984 (Box 1)
- Ellington, Duke 1983-1985, 1987 (Box 1)
- Farmington Ball 1984, 1986 (Box 2)
- Feasibility Study 1984 (Box 2)
- Feather, Leonard 1982-1985 (Box 2)
- Fitzgerald, Ella (Pablo Records) 1982-1983 (Box 2)
- Franklin Mint Corporation 1983 (Box 2)
- Fund-Raising Firms 1982-1985 (Box 2)
- Gift & Loan Agreement Forms n.d. (Box 2)
- Goodman, Benny 1982-1986 (Box 2)
- Hall of Fame Rationale 1983 (Box 2)
- Halls of Fame 1984 & n.d. (Box 2)
- Hendricks, Jon Concert 1984 (Box 2)
- Induction Ceremonies (2 folders) 1983-1985 (Box 2)
- Induction Criteria 1984 (Box 2)
- Jazz History Week 1983 (Box 2)
- McRee, Johnson, Jr. 1983 (Box 2)
- National Advisory Board 1983 (Box 2)
- NCAA Postseason Committee 1983-1984 (Box 2)
- National Endowment for the Arts - Jazz Section 1983-1984 (Box 2)
- National Portrait Gallery - Loan 1983 (Box 2)
- Newsletter - Hot Notes 1983-1986 (Box 2)
- Newsletter - Jazz Notes1985 Jun (Box 2)
- Newspaper Clippings 1983-1985, n.d. (Box 2)
- Obituaries of Jazzmen and Composers 1983-1985 (Box 2)
- Performance Contract Form 1984 Sep (Box 2)
- Photographs 1983-1984 (Box 2)
- Piedmont Council for the Arts 1983-1985 (Box 3)
- Playboy Jazz Festival Programs 1981 & 1983 (Box 3)
- Postal Permits & Fees 1983 (Box 3)
- Press Releases 1983 (Box 3)
- Printed Material 1974-1987 (Box 3)
- Private Foundations 1982-1985 (Box 3)
- Radio Advertising 1983 (Box 3)
- Receipt Forms n.d. (Box 3)
- Rich, Buddy 1983 (Box 3)
- Rutgers University - Dan Morgenstern 1983 (Box 3)
- Site Selection Committee 1982-1984 (Box 3)
- Sullivan, Maxine 1984-1985 (Box 3)
- Swinney, H. J. (Jerry) 1982-1983 (Box 3)
- Tanner, Paul 1983-1984 (Box 3)
- Telephone List 1985 (Box 3)
- TV/PBS/Video Tapes/NPR 1983, n.d. (Box 3)
- Trustees (Charter) 1983-1984 (Box 3)
- Virginia Foundation for the Humanities 1983 (Box 3)
- Virginia Jazz Consortium 1986-1987 (Box 3)
- Virginia's Rules re Contributions n.d. (Box 3)
- Washington, D.C. Jazz 1983-1985 (Box 3)
- West, George (JMU) 1983-1986 (Box 3)
- "Well-Wishers" 1983-1985 (Box 3)
- Women in Jazz Concert 1985-1986 (Box 3)
- The 1984 Compleat Jazz Calendar 1984 (Folder P-13)